Guide to the Walther Volbach Collection on Adolphe Appia
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Walther Volbach Collection on Adolphe Appia
1890-1969
GEN MSS 1014
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.58
(7 boxes) + 1 broadside
Volbach, Walther R. (Walther Richard), 1897-1996
Appia, Adolphe, 1862-1928
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, writings, newspaper and journal articles, photographs, and publications relating to Walther Volbach's research and writings on Adolphe Appia. Included are over sixty typescript essays, articles, and scenarios by Adolphe Appia, many bearing the stamp of the Fondation Adolphe Appia, Geneve. A typescript of Volbach's translation of many of these writings which was published as Adolphe Appia: Essays, Articles, and Scenarios in 1989, is included in the collection. The majority of correspondence consists of letters received by Volbach in the course of his research from Appia's relatives and friends including Appia's cousins Edmond Appia and Blanche Bingham, Appia's pupil and friend Jean Mercier, as well as librarians and fellow researchers, and colleagues with whom Volbach corresponded regarding publications by the American Educational Theatre Association. One reel of microfilm contains letters to Houston Stewart Chamberlain. A stage design by Appia for Act I, scene 1 of Parsifal is the only original design in the collection; however, his designs are represented by copy photographs that were used as illustrations for Volbach's book, Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 3 (microfilm reel): Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Adolphe Appia (1862-1928)
Adolphe François Appia was born in Geneva in 1862, the son of Louis Paul Amédée Appia, a successful surgeon and one of the founders of the Red Cross. While a youth, he became fascinated with the theater, but since his family considered it an inappropriate career choice, he studied music at Geneva, Paris, Leipzig, and Dresden. In 1884 Appia met Houston Stewart Chamberlain and became devoted to the works of Richard Wagner. With the help and encouragement of Chamberlain, he decided to become a designer and stage director.
Although he received scant recognition during his lifetime, Appia is regarded today as the father of modern stage lighting and design. His reforms of the antiquated nineteenth-century practice of stage design emphasized the significance of time and space, the relation of stage and auditorium, and the contrast of light and shadow. He devoted much of his lifework in particular to creating new productions of the operas of Richard Wagner. Appia died on February 29, 1928, in a nursing home near Nyon, Switzerland.
Appia set down his theories on stage set design in two books and several essays, but much of his writing was published only in the 1950s and 1960s. The Fondation Adolphe Appia has as its objective the publication of all his works and the furtherance of his ideas. For further biographical information, see Walther R. Volbach's Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile (1968).
Walther Volbach (1897-1996)
Walther Volbach was born in Mainz, Germany in 1897. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Munster in Westphalia in 1920, after completing his dissertation "The Development of Realism on the German Stage." In the 1920s he was an assistant to Max Reinhardt at the Deutsches Theater in Berlin, and also worked as a stage director of plays and operas at the State theaters in Stuttgart and Berlin, at the Municipal theaters in Zurich, Danzig and Kiel, and at Vienna's Volkstheater and Volksopera. He also served as an instructor at academies in Berlin, Vienna, and Kiel. After moving to the United States in the 1930s he taught and directed theater and opera in Ohio, Missouri, and Wisconsin. He was a professor in the Department of Theatre at Texas Christian University from 1946 until his retirement in 1965. His publications include Problems of Opera Production (1953); Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile (1968); and Adolphe Appia: Essays, Articles, and Scenarios (1989). He died in 1996.
Opera -- Production and direction; Opera -- Stage-setting and scenery; Set designers; Theater -- Production and direction; Theaters -- Stage-setting and scenery; Photographs; Set design drawings; Set designers; Appia, Adolphe, 1862-1928; Appia, Edmond, 1894-1961; Bingham, Blanche; Chamberlain, Houston Stewart, 1855-1927; Volbach, Walther R. (Walther Richard), 1897-1996; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883 ( Performances); American Educational Theatre Association
- Appia writings
  - "Adolphe Appia Essays and Scenarios" translated by R. Volbach, typescript, title page-page 492, 1979; 6 (Box 1)
  - Appia essays, typescripts, circa 1891-1927; 3
  - Appia essays, typescripts, circa 1891-1927; 2 (Box 2)
  - Appia essays, newspaper and journal articles, 1912-1964
  - "Appia's scenarios for Wagner's music dramas," typescripts, 1891-1926, undated; 3
  - "Adolphe Appia clippings and letters," photographic prints from microfilm, circa 1890-1929; 3
  - "Adolphe Appia clippings and letters," photographic prints from microfilm, circa 1890-1929 (Box 3)
  - Negative microfilm reel of letters from Adolphe Appia to H.S. [Houston Stewart] Chamberlain, undated
    Conditions Governing Access
    Use of original microfilm is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information
- Volbach research files
  - Articles about or related to Appia, circa 1899-1969; 3 (Box 3)
  - Articles about or related to Appia, circa 1899-1969; 4 (Box 4)
  - Annotated publications about or relating to Appia
    - Dussane, Béatrix. Dieux des planches. Paris: Flammarion, 1964
    - Faure, Élie. La Conquête. Paris: Éditions George Crès Et Cie, 1917
    - Gordon Craig. Paris: Bibliotèque Nationale, 1962
    - In Memoriam Hellerau. Freiburg: Romach and Co., 1960 (Box 5)
    - Jacques Copeau. Paris: Bibliotèque Nationale, 1963
    - Martin, Frank, et al. Emile Jaques-Dalcroze. Neuchâtel: Baconnière, 1965
  - Correspondence regarding Appia research
    - Appia, Edmond and Germaine, 1957-1962
    - Bingham, Blanche, 1924-1967
      Scope and Contents
      Includes three postcards from Adolphe Appia to Blanche Bingham and one to R. Penel, as well as reproductions of Appia letters from the "Bingham Collection."
    - Mercier, Jean, 1960-1968
    - Penel, Raymond, 1961-1965
    - Reyle, K., 1962-1969
    - Veinstein, Andre (Bibliotèque de l'Arsenal), 1958-1964
    - Zinsstag, Adolfe, 1961
    - Various correspondents, circa 1957-1969; 5 (Box 6)
  - Copy photographs of Appia, set designs, family crest, and other materials used as illustrations for Volbach's Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile, undated; 3
  - Copy photographs of Appia, set designs, family crest, and other materials used as illustrations for Volbach's Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile, undated (Box 7 (Oversize))
- Appia set design drawing of Parsifal, Act I, scene 1, undated (Box 8 (Broadside))